Well, as I mentioned, we've also been taking a closer look at the evacuation corridor south
from the northern tip of Gaza, which has been opened once again today. And our reporter
Merlyn Thomas from BBC Verify has been looking at that corridor and what the journey south
entails.
Israel has been ordering civilians in northern Gaza to move south for their safety as they
continue their offensive in the north. But what does that mean for civilians of Gaza?
Well, the Gaza Strip is one of the most densely populated areas on earth. There are over a
million people living in the northern part before this conflict started. And the Israeli
military have been telling people to move south using this specific road, Salah ad-Din.
It's one of the two main arteries connecting the north to the south. And we've seen some
of them, some of these people, moving south. As you can see, some of them are carrying
white flags, children, men, women, carrying with them all the possessions that they have.
Now, this footage was filmed by the AFP news agency on Monday. They spoke to one of those
Gazans on the road about her experience.
It was so scary. We saw tanks from both sides. We didn't see soldiers, just tanks. We held
our hands up and we kept walking. There were so many of us. We were holding white flags.
It's true that we were scared, but finally we made it through.
So how has the Israeli military been telling them? These are some of those pictures of
the mass drops of leaflets. Now, these white specks you can see here are those leaflets
dropping down from the Israeli military onto the ground. And they had messages urging locals
to move to the south for their own safety.
Now, they've also been posting messages on X. For example, this one. Today, the Israeli
military posted in Arabic that the main road here for evacuation, the one we've just been
talking about, would be open between 10 in the morning and 4 in the afternoon local time.
Yesterday, the Israeli military posted a video on X showing the civilians walking on Salahuddin
Road. Now, we've just paused this video here so you can see an Israeli tank in the foreground.
We've managed to verify this using the shape of the buildings and the road composition
as approximately three kilometres north of worthy Gaza, what the Israelis consider to
be the boundary between the north and south of Gaza.
We've also found this satellite imagery taken yesterday showing some of the stretch of the
road. And if you look closely, you can see here the outlines of people on the road moving
down the road down south. But if you look elsewhere in the image, you can also see the
damage to the buildings and the rubble and the debris that spilled out onto the road.
And this is what those people will have had to cross. And finally, if you look here, you
can actually spot an Israeli tank here too, right next to the road, which these people
will have had to walk past.
We've also been analysing satellite imagery captured on the 31st of October and the 3rd
of November. And using both of these, we've been able to assess the amount of damage on
the road and the buildings alongside it. So every single dot here, every single red dot
here represents damage of some kind to the road, whether that's craters on the road,
to the tarmac of the road or buildings damaged close to the road. We can't tell exactly when
this damage occurred, but let's take a closer look at these two areas here.
This one here, you can see a crater on the main road itself. This is what people will
have had to pass. And this, here you can see some buildings here in the middle destroyed
and the debris that scattered onto the road that people again will have had to cross.
Now we don't know how many people have used this road to move to safety. The UN suggested
that thousands have moved on one single day. But the question remains, as the fighting
continues in the north, how many more desperate people will have to make this choice?
Merlin Thomas from BBC Verify looking at that evacuation south. And the UN has estimated
that one and a half million people in Gaza are now displaced. Well, a little earlier,
I spoke to our colleague Rushdie Abualuf, our correspondent inside Gaza. He's in the
southern part of Gaza in Khan Yunis. And I asked him whether he had seen evidence of
more people moving south today.
The father who's carrying his son over his shoulder in the heat of the sun, it's unusual
weather here in Gaza. In November, it's really about 30 degrees in Gaza. But yes, people
under the sun were walking, carrying their kids, some of their belongings if they can.
And they made this journey into south. Why? Because the fighting in Gaza City is really
intensified. Taking very serious fight near the Al-Quds Hospital in Gaza. It's a Tell
el-Hawa area. It's a neighbourhood in the south-west of Gaza. As the tanks advance very
close to the hospital and people there, very few people remain in the area. And communication
is really hard. But I was talking to someone who fled this morning, and he said it was
a real gun battle in the area. Most of the buildings around that neighbourhood, from
the beginning of the Israeli attack on Gaza following the Hamas cross-border attack, this
area was heavily bombed from air for days. And now it's been bombed from sea and from
artillery units in the ground. The picture that I saw, it's really showing hundreds of
targets has been destroyed in this building. This area is considered most of the wealthy
people that live here. It's quite a new area that was built 25 years ago. Most of the buildings
are seven-storey buildings, like compound in the area. Most of the buildings were hit.
Either completely flattened to the ground or hit some of the great damage to some of
the buildings. The fighting also intensified near beach camp. Beach camp is the only refugee
camp in Gaza City with about 60,000, 70,000 people live in that camp. Most of them were
left, but people were still there and people were, many bodies are under their houses,
according to health ministry here. Fighting in that direction is north, west of Gaza.
It's all around the coastal road where all of the fighting is going on. But also, the
tanks are advancing from another position, which is south of the city. So now most of
the tanks are surrounding significant part of the Gaza City and they are advancing hard
into the Al-Quds Hospital, where about 14,000 people are taking the hospital as shelter,
as well as 100 patients. Yesterday, the hospital said that they can't move people, they can't
move patients from the hospital because there is no road around it, it's not damaged.